A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of Joan R. Dassin FA660
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of Joan R. Dassin
1959-1996 (bulk 1984-1996)
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA660
4.8 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Primarily contains program reviews and program history materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
Arranged in 4 series: 1. Field Offices and Regional Meeting. 2. Program Reviews. 3. Program History and Background. 4. Cuba.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation’s future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford’s international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee’s report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation’s aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
- Field Offices and Regional Meeting, I
  - Latin America and the Caribbean Regional Meeting, Apr 17-23, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Latin American Regional Meeting -- Briefing Books, Apr 18-20, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Andean Region Southern Cone, Apr 4, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Brazil Field Office, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Future of Lima, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Lima Office Closing, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Mexico Field Office, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Santiago Field Office, 1989-1994 (Box 1)
- Program Reviews, II
  - Developing Country Programs -- Latin Amerca and the Caribbean Program Review FY 1983, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Developing Country Programs -- Brazil Program Review FY 1985, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Developing Country Programs -- Latin America and the Caribbean Program Review FY 1987, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Developing Country Programs -- Andean Region and Southern Cone Program Review FY 1986, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Developing Country Programs -- Mexico and Central America Program Review FY 1987, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Developing Country Programs -- Latin America and the Caribbean Program Review FY 1988, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Developing Country Programs -- Andean Region and the Southern Cone Program Review FY 1989, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Developing Country Programs -- Mexico and Central America FY 1989, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Developing Country Programs -- Brazil FY 1989, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Research Agenda for US-Mexico Studies, Feb 14-16, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Caribbean-Latin America Biennial Budget FY 1990-1991, Apr 1989 (Box 2)
  - Mexico City -- FY 1990-1991 Biennial Budget Program Review, Apr 1989 (Box 2)
  - Rio de Janiero -- FY 1990-1991 Biennial Budget Program Review, Apr 1989 (Box 2)
  - Haiti Democratic Needs Assessment, May 1989 (Box 2)
  - Developing Country Programs -- Latin America and the Caribbean FY 1989, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Caribbean -- Latin American Regional -- FY 1990 Program Review, Apr 1990 (Box 2)
  - Overview of Program -- Brazil, Sep 1990 (Box 2)
  - Latin America Regional -- FY 1991 Program Review, Apr 1991 (Box 2)
  - International Directory of Foundations with Grant Programs in Latin America, Summer 1991 (Box 2)
  - Overview of Program -- Mexico and Central America, Mar 1992 (Box 2)
  - A Summary of the Proceedings of the Ford Foundation Latin America and the Caribbean Program Review, May 6, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Program Review -- Caribbean, May 1992 (Box 2)
  - Latin America Regional -- Program Review, May 1992 (Box 2)
  - Mexico City -- Program Review, May 1992 (Box 2)
  - Rio de Janeiro -- Program Review, May 1992 (Box 2)
  - Santiago -- Program Review, May 1992 (Box 2)
  - Caribbean -- Program Reviews, Mar 1993 (Box 2)
  - Latin America Regional -- Program Reviews, Mar 1993 (Box 2)
  - Mexico City -- Program Reviews, Mar 1993 (Box 2)
  - Rio de Janeiro -- Program Reviews, Mar 1993 (Box 2)
  - Santiago -- Program Reviews, Mar 1993 (Box 2)
  - Biennial Program Review, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Program Review, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Board Text / Program Reviews, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Program Review March 1995, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
- Program History and Background, III
  - Background Papers, 1987-1992 (Box 3)
  - Caribbean Planning, 1992-1994 (Box 3)
  - Cuba/Haiti Background, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
  - Draft Brochure, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Environment and Development in Latin America, 1993 (Box 3)
  - History of the Latin American Program, 1961-1992 (Box 3)
  - Program History, 1967-1989 (Box 3)
  - History of the Latin American Program, 1959-1980 (Box 3)
  - History of the Latin American Program, 1972-1991 (Box 3)
  - History of the Latin America, 1970-1996 (Box 3)
  - Program Reports (1/2), 1994 (Box 3)
  - Program Reports (2/2), 1994 (Box 3)
  - Reproductive Health / Background, 1991-1995 (Box 3)
- Cuba, IV
  - Cuba, 1988-1994 (Box 4)
  - Cuba DAP Proposals [PHOTOS], 1980-1983 (Box 4)
  - Cuba -- Jeff Puryear Information, 1967-1985 (Box 4)
  - Cuban-Americans Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Cuba -- Miscellaneous Information -- Staff Meeting, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Cuba Background II, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
  - Cuba -- Ford Programs -- History, 1967-1989 (Box 4)